<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Michelle's [uncreative adjective] Blog</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog/" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Michelle Tran</name>
        <email>email@michtran.ca</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2022-03-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Project Risk and Time Estimation</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-03-20-project_risk.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-03-20-project_risk.html</id>
    <published>2022-03-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on March 20, 2022</em>
    
</div>

<p>After years of leading projects, I feel like I’ve finally stopped having an aversion to setting time estimates, and have accepted that they’re a necessary part of project management. Giving these values always feel like I’m just making up a number for the sake of putting in a deadline (ie. <em>bullshitting</em> my way through to project completion). However a shift of mindset from being <em>accurate</em> to doing better <em>expectation management</em> made it easier to accept that putting in a projected deadline is not really that bad.</p>
<p>So this is an article about how I’ve come to not be scared off by work estimation.</p>
<h2 id="why-it-is-important-to-give-a-target-completion">Why it is important to give a target completion</h2>
<p>I will admit that giving a completion estimation is in many ways, <em>actually</em> quite arbitrary. There will be many factors that you will not be able to control, like one of your team member’s employment status or unpredictable increase in oncall reactive maintenance. So, deadlines can shift based on these factors.</p>
<p>However, the importance of giving a target completion, (even when we all know that they tend to slip), is that you can set some expectations to other people in the organization about when they might expect a particular feature. For instance, the sales department will need to know when a feature is going to launch so that they know when they can start “selling” the feature. Customer support will need to know when the feature launch so that they can collate the training materials required to train up customer support agents before the feature is actually launched. We don’t launch in a vacuum. We have other groups relying on what’s coming. If we miss our target, it will affect the delivery of these other dependencies.</p>
<h2 id="is-there-value-in-work-estimation">Is there value in work estimation?</h2>
<p>I have yet to find a good technique to do work estimation in a project well. Generally I found that the better you understand the problem/technology/code/team members, the better your technical breakdown, which means the better your estimate. The more details you can get in your plan, the better the estimate.</p>
<p>The work breakdown and estimation is generally a good start as the initial estimate. This is usually the number I’m most iffy about because there are lots of caveats about the estimation. For instance, if you need to collaborate with another team then the assumption is that there will be <em>no friction</em> between how the developers in each team work together. Or there might be something that we thought was easy, but has turned out more complex than initially planned.</p>
<p>So when I do time or work estimation now, I usually give the work estimation <em>with</em> some sort of risk assessment.</p>
<h2 id="time-estimation-is-about-risk-management">Time Estimation is about Risk Management</h2>
<p>So this leads me to my central thesis: time estimation is about expectation management is about risk management. Using the transitive property on the previous statement, <em>time estimation is about risk management</em>.</p>
<p>Project risk usually occurs in 2 forms:</p>
<ul>
<li>Planning risk</li>
<li>Execution risk</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-is-planning-risk">What is planning risk?</h2>
<p>Planning risk usually involves informational uncertainty that has the potential to affect the project deadline.</p>
<p>These risks may look like:</p>
<ul>
<li>unclear requirements (do I have everything I need to work on the project?)</li>
<li>inherent complexity, or “the known landmines”; some projects have a piece that resists decomposition and/or is logically complex.<br />
</li>
<li>overly long or complex critical paths</li>
<li>technology or tools that the team isn’t familiar with</li>
<li>scaling issues</li>
<li>not enough people to work on the project (team too small for the project ambition)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-is-execution-risk">What is execution risk?</h2>
<p>Execution risks usually involve emergent issues that come up as the project progresses.</p>
<p>These risks may look like:</p>
<ul>
<li>dependency on external team</li>
<li>not enough people to work on the project (assigned people pulled into other company priorities)</li>
<li>new unforseen requirements</li>
<li>requirements being more complex than initially planned</li>
<li>operational load or other non-project priorities</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how-to-use-these-risks-with-time-estimates">How to use these risks with time estimates?</h2>
<p>I no longer provide time estimates without their context anymore. The initial estimate will include the work breakdown. Then status updates (usually on weekly basis) will include:</p>
<ul>
<li>known risks, their probability and impact (can we eat this risk?)</li>
<li>any major decisions made in project and/or a specify risk item</li>
<li>forecasted completion date (can be adjusted based on new risks)</li>
</ul>
<p>Risk tends to change as the project progresses, so risks early in the project (like those risks that usually occur in the planning phase) will get less risky as we get more clarity on their impact and resolution. Execution risks may crop up unexpectedly, so we need to highlight them and adjust timelines as they emerge.</p>
<p>When highlighting the probability and impact of risk, it’s worth thinking about the idea of materialized vs. unmaterialized risk. For example, integrating with a new vendor starts as an unmaterialized risk - we aren’t familiar with the accuracy of their documentation and the reliability of their APIs, but as long as we’ve done what we can with reading their documentation, there’s not much else that can be done until we actually start integrating. If, once we start tackling this integration, we’re running into all sorts of problems, that’s a materialized risk, and requires more direct action/potential deadline adjustment.</p>
<p>This approach is more about <em>communication of expectations</em>, and less about <em>accurate forecasting</em>.</p>
<h2 id="ive-identified-risks-how-do-i-deal-with-them">I’ve identified risks, how do I deal with them?</h2>
<p>This is not an exhaustive list of things that I’ve done with risk that I’ve identified in projects:</p>
<ul>
<li>being explicit about the risk and the potential effects of risk is the first step! unknown or untracked risks are the riskiest!</li>
<li>getting more clarity on the risk will help derisk it (ie. scaling issues, if we can find some numbers to project the expected load, then we’re derisking it)</li>
<li>new process can also help derisk (ie. define cross team syncs to more frequently address cross team collaboration)</li>
<li>recalibrate the projection, taking into account the risk (ie. given that we’re not sure about the load requirements and the potential necessary steps to fix it, are we still confident about the project projection?)</li>
<li>rescope some features (ie. we might be able to hit our target date if we don’t add a cache layer)</li>
<li>for risks associated with landmines/critical paths, we can timebox, swarm or seek additional feedback</li>
<li>wait and see. Sometimes we might want to wait a bit more to see how we progress (e.g. in the case where it seems like we’re slowly veering off forecast, we might call it out and give it a bit more time. While “do nothing” shouldn’t always be the default, it can be a legitimate choice when there isn’t enough of an impetus for concrete action yet.</li>
<li>eat the risk and deal with it after the project. We need to ensure that track this risk and add it to our backlog.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I’ve got a system that currently works for me. Being explicit about risks help set the expectation to stakeholders, and the regular communication builds trust with management. Ultimately, I think this is what matters most in managing projects in a corporate environment. It’s kind of a change from start-up life, where you just hack your way to a product. But when you’ve got more moving pieces to juggle, risk management is the key to giving better time estimates for project completion.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>Acknowledgement:</em> Thanks to Dennis Poon for helping me refine the ideas and thinking through planning vs execution risks.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Why I Read a lot of Books</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-02-23-why_i_read.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-02-23-why_i_read.html</id>
    <published>2022-02-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on February 23, 2022</em>
    
</div>

<p>I try to read 52 books a year. There are people who read more, but many more who read less. A lot of it is fiction, but I also read a lot of non-fiction books too. People who are impressed by how much I read usually ask, <em>“How do you remember everything that you read?”</em>. My answer to that is usually: <em>I don’t</em>.</p>
<p>If I don’t retain everything that I read, then why do I still try to read so many books? Wouldn’t it be better if I read less, but retained more?</p>
<p>I think that reading a lot of books helps me build <em>intuition</em>. I may not remember exactly what lead me to think a certain way, but the accumulated knowledge of the thoroughly edited books that I’ve read leads me to having a better judgement on things.</p>
<p>The classic example is fiction. There are studies that show that people who read a lot of fiction tends to be <a href="https://www.discovermagazine.com/mind/how-reading-fiction-increases-empathy-and-encourages-understanding">more empathetic</a>. Do we remember necessarily which character fits which real life person/situation? Probably not. But the accumulation of the experiences of characters that you read will give you a better understanding of the vast range of human thought.</p>
<p>So, although I don’t retain most of what I read (and I’m also terrible with quoting books), I read because I enjoy reading and also because I’m building my intuition on whatever topic interests me.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>So my Computer Broke in 2022...</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-02-14-new-computer.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-02-14-new-computer.html</id>
    <published>2022-02-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on February 14, 2022</em>
    
</div>

<p>For the past 5 years, my main computer has been a 15&quot; Macbook Pro. It was the computer that I acquired through work, which I then purchased off of them when I left. For a personal device, it is way over powered. Most of my computer needs are:</p>
<ul>
<li>watching videos</li>
<li>web surfing</li>
<li>online banking</li>
<li>buying stuff online</li>
<li>lightweight editor (mostly to modify markdown files)</li>
<li>ssh for managing various servers</li>
<li>portability for when I went travelling, and/or around the house</li>
</ul>
<p>As my Macbook’s battery is on the verge of explosion, I had the option to re-evaluate my computing options and potentially save some money.</p>
<p>So… what devices do I still have…</p>
<h2 id="my-old-haxxor-lenovo-t420s">My old haxxor Lenovo T420s…</h2>
<p>The first thing I dug into was my old T420s. I shamelessly installed it back in 2016 with Debian and Xmonad. That was back when I actually had time on my hands.</p>
<p>So, coming back to this super custom machine in 2022, I had already forgotten how to use it. Luckily, I wrote a blog article on how I got it to work (like <code>wicd</code> to connect to internet) so I was able to reverse engineer stuff I did to make the computer mildly usable. But it made me think about how I gradually made my Macbook Pro my main computer over time because it <em>just worked</em>.</p>
<p>As I grow older with limited capacity to learn and customize my habits, the mental overhead of these super cool custom things isn’t really worth the time.</p>
<p>Is a tiling window manager cool? Yes. But it’s also extra knowledge that I need to invest time into making a habit. Not to mention that it’s not exactly transferable. Knowing how to use this super customized computer will not translate to knowing how to use any random computer. So, this was a long winded way to say that I’m unlikely to install a TWM again in my next computer.</p>
<p>The other annoyance is that the hard drive is also end of life. It’s an SSD I bought around 2013, and although I stayed up late to reinstall it with a more usable OS, (was super nostalgic… reminded me of late nights waiting for things to work) it still ran too slowly for me. So in order for me to make this work as a main device, I’ll at least need to get a new hard drive.</p>
<p>The last annoyance is that the battery is pretty unusable, so I can’t expect to be able to use it away from a power source. However, at least the machine works without a battery, which is better than the modern laptops/devices that can’t run at all when the battery dies.</p>
<h2 id="my-phone-is-also-a-computer">My phone is also a computer</h2>
<p>Most of my browsing is currently on my phone. Admittedly, my phone is probably powerful enough for most of my everyday computer needs. It is super portable, has a decent browser and I already sometimes use it to play videos and music.</p>
<p>The problem is that my phone screen is annoyingly small for any terminal work. Also, it’s the device that I’m most likely to lose, so I probably don’t want to put too many of my secret keys on it. It’s probably best suited as an emergency backup device.</p>
<h2 id="how-about-my-work-laptop">How about my work laptop?</h2>
<p>My work laptop has too much spyware. So having personal stuff on it is out of the question.</p>
<h2 id="samsung-galaxy-tab-s2">Samsung Galaxy Tab S2</h2>
<p>I inherited this relatively old tablet (2015) earlier this year. I use it mainly to show videos to my toddler. But, there were a few things that I was able to do to make it feel more like a laptop.</p>
<p>I was able to connect my wired ErgoDox keyboard via a micro-USB dongle that we bought many years ago.</p>
<p>Development apps need to be downloaded via F-droid. The apps downloaded through Google Play didn’t work due to Google’s weirdness around permissions.</p>
<p>But I was able to get SSH access through Termux, and draft this blog article via GitJournal. I can upload this blog article to my GitHub Pages site by using <code>mgit</code> and do random code fixes via Acode. So current status: can blog.</p>
<p>The only downsides of this tablet is that the battery life is pretty bad (that was exactly the reason why the original owner gave it to me). Also, I can’t charge it on my desk because I don’t have a micro-USB cable that is long enough to go from my desk to the power outlet. So I need to make sure the tablet is charged before I to use it for an extended amount of time.</p>
<p>The tablet also can’t multitask as well as a computer, which can be a plus or minus. It helps create focus, but is also annoying if I want to do many things at the same time.</p>
<h2 id="what-now">What now?</h2>
<p>My Macbook Pro is eligible for a free battery replacement. So I took it to the Apple Store to get it replaced. However, the part needs to be ordered internationally, so it’ll be a few weeks until it can be fixed.</p>
<p>At the moment, using the tablet is good enough for my usual usage. But it’s probably not going to be sufficient for the long term. Or at least I need more time to see how it pans out.</p>
<p>I’m probably due for a computer upgrade anyways. In all likelihood, I’m probably going to go for whatever new Macbook Air comes out this year.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
