<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Michelle's [uncreative adjective] Blog</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog/" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Michelle Tran</name>
        <email>email@michtran.ca</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2020</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2021-01-01-retrospective.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2021-01-01-retrospective.html</id>
    <published>2021-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2021</em>
    
</div>

<p>There have been several major life events for me this year.</p>
<p>The obvious big event that affected everyone is the pandemic. Jobs that were not remote friendly needed to shift to being more accepting of totally remote work. My job was not <em>really</em> remote but most of my colleagues were already coming into the office once a week. So, this was just the catalyst for it to be completely remote.</p>
<p>I found out that I was pregnant early in the year, and gave birth to a healthy baby at the end of summer. This meant that the pandemic happened throughout most of my pregnancy. There was some anxiety about possibly getting sick during the pregnancy, but lockdowns and working from home meant less chance of exposure.</p>
<p>We also bought a house at the start of lockdown. I think we were quite lucky because the market is still pretty crazy in Toronto.</p>
<p>I’ve learned that the hardest part of being a new parent is figuring out who to listen to for advice and what to ignore. Doctors are generally reliable for medical advice, but they don’t necessarily know how to schedule your baby’s naps or how to help you with breast feeding. There are consultants for these, which I had been fortunate enough to afford or get through work. It does make me sympathize with poor families who may not have access to these resources.</p>
<p>My baby is cuter than I had expected and the love is overwhelming.</p>
<p>I managed to reach my reading goal this year. However, my reading has slowed down since I became a parent, so let’s see how it goes next year.</p>
<p>I really miss travelling.</p>
<p>I will be back to work in a few months, which I’m looking forward to. And hopefully with the vaccine discovered, next year will go back to something sort of resembling the life before the pandemic.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2019</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2020-01-01-Retrospective_2019.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2020-01-01-Retrospective_2019.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2020</em>
    
</div>

<p>I’ve been back in Toronto for one year now. Since I’m back in North America, I can’t say that I’ve travelled very much this year.</p>
<p>I did take a short business trip to Ottawa in February. I got to see Carleton University (for the first time) and saw the unfinished subway.</p>
<p>The biggest thing to have happened to me is that I changed jobs… again. There were a couple of reasons why I left the job, but the 2 main reasons were related to my commute (45 minutes each way) and a developing fear that I was not technically rounded enough to adapt to new technologies. So my new job is now much closer to home and is primarily using a different technology than what I’ve been programming in the past 6 years. I still have in my mind, an idea that I should try working in a consultancy at some point to get more technical breadth.</p>
<p>I got my piano back this summer. I’ve been learning a few pieces, mostly Debussy and Chopin. In particular: Reverie (Debussy), Waltz in C# Minor (Chopin) Nocturne in Eb Major (Chopin), and Waltz in Ab Major (Chopin). Maybe someday I can play the Revolutionary Etude (Chopin) and Clair de Lune (Debussy).</p>
<p>I’ve also given up on alcohol since October. The most surprising result from this was that it has saved me a lot of money (well, it should be obvious considering how expensive alcohol is here). I also haven’t really missed it very much, but that’s partly because I don’t socialize much anymore. I think I will probably go back to drinking at some point, but probably less than I use to drink when living in Europe.</p>
<p>I’ve also got myself a new smart phone this year. It’s mostly for my new job, which requires me to be oncall regularly.</p>
<p>I also managed to read up to 100 books this year. Admittedly, it became a pain as I got closer to 100 books. My goal is always only 52 books, and I always go past it with a wide margin. At some point when I reached 80 books this year, I thought that I should maybe really try to hit 100 books. However, I started only reading for the sake of hitting the goal and found myself <em>dreading</em> reading after my 100th book. Anyways, I hope to be less ambitious this year and not pressure myself to read when I don’t feel like it.</p>
<p>Lastly, the only travelling I did this year was to a resort in Cuba over Christmas. It was underwhelming; lots of sun, sand and not much else otherwise. I regret going over Christmas, as I found that I had wished that I was with my family instead. Anyways, I will probably avoid going to resorts in the future and probably also not travel over Christmas.</p>
<p>I kind of regret not focusing more on my health this year, so maybe I’ll try to exercise regularly and eating better. I also didn’t draw or paint much this year. Hopefully with the time saved on my commute, I will feel motivated to draw again.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2018</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2019-01-01-New-Year.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2019-01-01-New-Year.html</id>
    <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2019</em>
    
</div>

<p>This was both an exciting year, and also luckily not too eventful (ie, no more health incident).</p>
<p>I started off the year with a trip to Vietnam and Hong Kong. We went with family, and the experience made me reconsider staying in Berlin.</p>
<p>I went to Malaga for a work trip in April. It was quite nice, but also too early in the year to enjoy lying on the beach.</p>
<p>In June, we travelled to Ireland and did a road trip around the whole island. It was very beautiful and I did quite a few paintings. I found the relaxed nature of the trip much more conducive for painting.</p>
<p>We went to Poland in July to visit family. On our way back, we also passed by Malbork, Toruń, and Bydgoszcz.</p>
<p>I went to Europython in Edinburgh in July. I enjoyed it more than other conferences because I was meeting up with collegues. I also went to Pycon Canada in November. It was also alright because I was not creeped out (unlike the meetups/conferences I’ve been to in Berlin). I think Berlin was a particular bad case, as I never had problems in Seattle or London either.</p>
<p>I went to Venice and Florence in August. It was a very nice trip; both were touristy cities, but the weather was exceptional. I went with my brother, so it was a nice sibling bonding time. It was also the first trip I’ve been where I didn’t plan things out in details, and so we ended up sitting at cafes sipping coffee or wine for hours. I think I really enjoy this form of travel, and maybe can do more of this in the future.</p>
<p>I also made the decision to resign at the company I was working at in August. It was difficult, but I think it was the correct decision. I definitely had a major sense of relief after I resigned.</p>
<p>Soon after I resigned, I also got offered a new job in Toronto.</p>
<p>I moved back to Toronto at the end of October. So we had the rest of the summer in Berlin. It was a beautiful dry summer, and we spent it eating icecream in the park. It’s still too early to tell if I regret the decision. I think Berlin will always have a place in my heart, but seeing family and friends every few weeks is a definite plus.</p>
<p>Before returning to Toronto, we spent a week on the Azores. It was a relaxing holiday; we ate a lot of steak and dipped in many hotsprings.</p>
<p>I suspect that we will travel less now that we’re back in Canada. I’ve got half the amount of vacation days as my previous company. Also, adjusting to a non-remote work environment wasn’t too difficult. However, I definitely miss the freedom of working from home.</p>
<p>In terms of goals for this year, I think I want to do more with art and also more for my career.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
