<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Michelle's [uncreative adjective] Blog</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog/" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Michelle Tran</name>
        <email>email@michtran.ca</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2021</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-01-01-retrospective.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2022-01-01-retrospective.html</id>
    <published>2022-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2022</em>
    
</div>

<p>COVID is still a thing. It has dampened any motivation (but not desire, unfortunately) to travel. I’ve been finding myself browsing travel blogs at various times during the year.</p>
<p>I started off the year still on parental leave, and headed back to work in March. Although I enjoyed my time with my baby, it was somewhat of a relief to go back to work.</p>
<p>The COVID deniers, antivaxxers, antimaskers have made me lose faith in humanity. On the plus side, we have a fairly OK vaccination rate in Canada. We should really send our surplus vaccines to countries that have shortages.</p>
<p>I’m learning Chinese and have reached about HSK 3. I stalled here because I’ve already finished Duolingo and haven’t really had motivation to continue with my Chinese textbooks. I bought a bunch of graded Chinese readers, which I’ve been going through slowly. 我因该学多中文，但是我没有时间。 我的孩子有太多精力， 所以我每天就得很累了。</p>
<p>I read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/56481725-staff-engineer">Staff Engineer by Will Larson</a>, and that motivated me a bit career wise. It’s hard to focus on it when my toddler keeps getting sick from daycare. The paediatrician said that it will be like this for the first year of daycare/school.</p>
<p>I’ve been neglecting my blog. I wrote some articles that I posted internally to company wiki. Maybe I’ll sanitize those and add them to my personal blog as well. They are mainly about risk and project management.</p>
<p>I’ve also been neglecting my health, and the Christmas sweets aren’t helping.</p>
<p>I managed to read 70 books this year. My favourite is <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11737287-llama-llama-wakey-wake">Llama Llama Wakey Wake</a>.</p>
<p>Parenting a toddler is surprisingly fun. But I’m glad I get to stick them in daycare.</p>
<p>I didn’t do much in terms of side projects. I migrated this blog to using GitHub Actions to deploy (rather than my copying the build files into a dedicated repo). I’m impressed that I managed to find the time to do that at all this year.</p>
<p>I bought a homeless person a coffee one day, and another homeless person meals from McDonalds on another day. Handing out cash might be more useful, but I don’t usually keep cash on me.</p>
<p>I didn’t end up catching omicron COVID, even though I was constantly in a sick cycle with my toddler starting from September. However, we managed to get a booster before year end. Yay.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2020</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2021-01-01-retrospective.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2021-01-01-retrospective.html</id>
    <published>2021-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2021</em>
    
</div>

<p>There have been several major life events for me this year.</p>
<p>The obvious big event that affected everyone is the pandemic. Jobs that were not remote friendly needed to shift to being more accepting of totally remote work. My job was not <em>really</em> remote but most of my colleagues were already coming into the office once a week. So, this was just the catalyst for it to be completely remote.</p>
<p>I found out that I was pregnant early in the year, and gave birth to a healthy baby at the end of summer. This meant that the pandemic happened throughout most of my pregnancy. There was some anxiety about possibly getting sick during the pregnancy, but lockdowns and working from home meant less chance of exposure.</p>
<p>We also bought a house at the start of lockdown. I think we were quite lucky because the market is still pretty crazy in Toronto.</p>
<p>I’ve learned that the hardest part of being a new parent is figuring out who to listen to for advice and what to ignore. Doctors are generally reliable for medical advice, but they don’t necessarily know how to schedule your baby’s naps or how to help you with breast feeding. There are consultants for these, which I had been fortunate enough to afford or get through work. It does make me sympathize with poor families who may not have access to these resources.</p>
<p>My baby is cuter than I had expected and the love is overwhelming.</p>
<p>I managed to reach my reading goal this year. However, my reading has slowed down since I became a parent, so let’s see how it goes next year.</p>
<p>I really miss travelling.</p>
<p>I will be back to work in a few months, which I’m looking forward to. And hopefully with the vaccine discovered, next year will go back to something sort of resembling the life before the pandemic.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Retrospective on 2019</title>
    <link href="http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2020-01-01-Retrospective_2019.html" />
    <id>http://michtran.ca/blog//blog/posts/2020-01-01-Retrospective_2019.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
<em>Posted on January  1, 2020</em>
    
</div>

<p>I’ve been back in Toronto for one year now. Since I’m back in North America, I can’t say that I’ve travelled very much this year.</p>
<p>I did take a short business trip to Ottawa in February. I got to see Carleton University (for the first time) and saw the unfinished subway.</p>
<p>The biggest thing to have happened to me is that I changed jobs… again. There were a couple of reasons why I left the job, but the 2 main reasons were related to my commute (45 minutes each way) and a developing fear that I was not technically rounded enough to adapt to new technologies. So my new job is now much closer to home and is primarily using a different technology than what I’ve been programming in the past 6 years. I still have in my mind, an idea that I should try working in a consultancy at some point to get more technical breadth.</p>
<p>I got my piano back this summer. I’ve been learning a few pieces, mostly Debussy and Chopin. In particular: Reverie (Debussy), Waltz in C# Minor (Chopin) Nocturne in Eb Major (Chopin), and Waltz in Ab Major (Chopin). Maybe someday I can play the Revolutionary Etude (Chopin) and Clair de Lune (Debussy).</p>
<p>I’ve also given up on alcohol since October. The most surprising result from this was that it has saved me a lot of money (well, it should be obvious considering how expensive alcohol is here). I also haven’t really missed it very much, but that’s partly because I don’t socialize much anymore. I think I will probably go back to drinking at some point, but probably less than I use to drink when living in Europe.</p>
<p>I’ve also got myself a new smart phone this year. It’s mostly for my new job, which requires me to be oncall regularly.</p>
<p>I also managed to read up to 100 books this year. Admittedly, it became a pain as I got closer to 100 books. My goal is always only 52 books, and I always go past it with a wide margin. At some point when I reached 80 books this year, I thought that I should maybe really try to hit 100 books. However, I started only reading for the sake of hitting the goal and found myself <em>dreading</em> reading after my 100th book. Anyways, I hope to be less ambitious this year and not pressure myself to read when I don’t feel like it.</p>
<p>Lastly, the only travelling I did this year was to a resort in Cuba over Christmas. It was underwhelming; lots of sun, sand and not much else otherwise. I regret going over Christmas, as I found that I had wished that I was with my family instead. Anyways, I will probably avoid going to resorts in the future and probably also not travel over Christmas.</p>
<p>I kind of regret not focusing more on my health this year, so maybe I’ll try to exercise regularly and eating better. I also didn’t draw or paint much this year. Hopefully with the time saved on my commute, I will feel motivated to draw again.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
